The first free settlement ever in
America lies under these waters. The
settlers of Watauga Valley, Tennessee
had a charter, a constitution, and a
government before America was even
America. They were some hardy mountain
men who marched over the Appalachian
Mountains to settle in that valley in
defiance of the English Crown. They were
also in defiance of the natives who
really owned this land. They were
outlaws on both sides. The natives at
first thought about killing them, but
then saw the rocky land they settled
[music] in and figured, "Ah, we'll just
leave them. They'll be dead after the
first winter." Little did they know the
rocky [music] soil right here very much
resembles the farmland of Ireland where
these settlers were adapted growing
potatoes. The first winter passed and
natives came back to see the settlers
living happily full of potatoes and they
were shocked. The natives decided to let
them stay and wound up cutting off a
piece of land for sale to the settlers.
Later on they played a pivotal part in
the Revolutionary War. They had a female
that made gunpowder and supplied it to
the revolutionary army. This lady was
mining saltpeter in the 1700s to shoot
down the redcoats. Later on the men of
Watauga Valley hiked over the mountain
on the Overmountain Victory Trail to go
fight the pivotal battle of King's
Mountain in Cowpens, South Carolina to
turn the entire southern theater towards
the revolutionary cause. These dudes
defied the British Crown, bartered with
the natives, and basically won the
Revolutionary War. Where are they now? I
don't see them anywhere. Sometime around
the 1920s the federal government they
had fought and bled for decided that
they needed to build a hydroelectric dam
[music] right here to put electricity to
the developing towns. And the settlers
of Watauga Valley were bought out by
eminent domain. They got paid minimum
wage to help chip out the mountains you
see right there to build the dam you see
right here to flood the houses that you
no longer see down there. It's the same
story we've seen over and over again.
Badass men do badass things then get
tricked by people with paper.